Let's try our staging test out from start to finish.
让我们从头到尾地尝试一下我们的 "staging" 测试
So now in order for us to test this staging test, from end to end,
现在，为了从头到尾地进行 "staging" 测试
you first going to need to get our sub ID for the channeling fear F
首先你需要获取 "Chainlink VRF" 的 "SubId"
then we're going to need to deploy our contract using the sub ID,
接着我们再用这个 "SubId" 部署我们的合约
we're going to need to register the contract with chain link VRF. And it's somebody
我们需要在 "Chainlink VRF" 上注册合约以及它的 "SubId"
we're going to then need to register it with chain link keepers. And then of course, we're going to run the staging tests.
然后我们需要注册 "Chainlink Keepers"，再然后当然就是运行 "staging" 测试了
So let's do it.
那么，让我们开始吧
So first thing we're going to need to do is what?
首先我们需要做的是什么呢？
Get our sub ID for chain link VRF. Okay, great.
获取 "Chainlink VRF" 的 "SubId"，好的
So we're going to come over to VRF dot chain dot link.
我们来到 "vrf.chain.link"
And we're going to need to create a new subscription.
然后我们需要创建一个新的订阅
If we don't have enough rink B eath.
如果我们没有足够的 "Rinkeby ETH"
Let's we want to head over to the full blockchain solidity course,
我们就前往 "full-blockchain-solidity-course"
here, we're going to scroll down. And we're going to look for the recommended test and here, which is ranked v.
在这里，我们往下拉，找到我们在这里推荐的测试网，也就是 "Rinkeby"
And we're going to use the faucets link to get some Rigby link,
接着我们用 "faucets link" 来获取一些 "Rinkeby" 和 "Link"
run Fosses dot chain dot link, let's switch over from COVID to a cerium. Rigby,
运行 "faucets.chain.link"，并且从 "Kovan" 切换到 "Ethereum Rinkeby"
we know we're going to need some link and some eath. So let's just go ahead and get both.
我们既需要一些 "Link" 也需要一些 "ETH"，所以我们把它们都选上
Alright, great now that our transaction has gone through,
很好，我们的交易已经通过了
let's just double check our wallet here.
让我们再次检查一下我们的钱包
And it looks like we do indeed have Ethereum here.
看来我们确实已经获得一些 "Ethereum" 了
And if you don't see the link, you can head over to link token contracts,
如果你看不到 "Link"，就前往 "link token contracts"
Link token contracts in the chain link documentation.
"LINK Token Contracts" 就在 "Chainlink" 的文档里
We'll scroll down to Rigby, we'll grab this contract address
往下拉到 "Rinkeby"，获取这个合约的地址
import tokens and we'll paste it in here.
点击 "import tokens"，并且把它粘贴到这里
Add Custom tokens, import tokens. Great.
点击 "Add Custom Token" 以及 "Import Tokens"，很好
Now I can see my eath and my link here, perfect.
现在我就可以看到我的 "ETH" 以及 "Link" 了，完美
We have some eath we have some link,
现在我们有了一些 "ETH" 以及 "Link"
let's head over to V REF subscription management. And we're going to create a new subscription.
让我们转到 "VRF" 的订阅管理，并创建一个新的订阅
Again, we could totally do this programmatically,
再次强调，我们完全可以使用程序化的方式
because the user interface here is only helping us facilitate call contracts to the registration contract that's completely decentralized and on chain.
因为用户界面只是帮助我们简化对链上去中心化合约的调用和注册
So let's go ahead and create subscription
现在让我们继续，创建订阅
will create subscription will confirm the transaction and Metamask on the Rinkeby network
我们点击 "Create subscription"，在 MetaMask 中确认交易，并且是在 "Rinkeby" 网络上
will do a little bit of wading in great once it's gone through, you can go ahead and click the add funds button.
稍微等一下，很好，通过之后你就可以点击 "Add funds" 按钮继续了
I'm going to show you what it looks like if you accidentally refresh and jump off though.
我会向你展示一下，如果你不小心刷新并跳了出来会怎么样
So if you refresh and you go back to veer off the chain dot link,
如果你点了刷新，就需要返回到 "vrf.chain.link"
you should have a new active subscription.
这时你应该会有一个新的活跃("Active")订阅
And you'll see this number here. If you click on it, this is your subscription ID great.
如果你看一下这里的数字，点击一下，这其实就是你的 "subscriptionId"
So we can actually take this, come back to our code into our helper Hardhead config.
这样我们就可以获取这个数字，回到我们的 "hepler-hardhat-config" 的代码中
And we can paste our subscription ID under subscription ID for our Rinkeby network here. Awesome.
现在我们就可以把我们的 "subscriptionId" 粘贴到我们的 "rinkeby" 网络这里了，干得好
Now that we have a subscription we can see it's not funded with any link.
现在我们在 "Subscription" 里看到，这里还没有注入任何 "LINK"
So we don't have any Oracle gas here. And we don't have any consumers.
所以我们现在还没有预言机 "gas"，也没有任何 "consumers"
Right our consumer is going to be a raffle or a lottery contract.
对于我们来说，"consumers" 就是抽奖或者说彩票合约
So let's add some funds first and we don't need to add A whole lot because we're only going to be testing once.
让我们先注入一些资金，我们不需要往里面加很多，因为我们打算只测试一次而已
So let's go just go ahead and add to link here,
让我们继续，给它添加一些 "Link"
this number might change depending on different costs of the test nets and how much link token there's available.
这个数字可能会根据不同测试网的不同花费以及可用 "Link" 的多少而改变
So if you're actually working on a main net,
如果你是在主网上运行
be sure to head over Doc's touching that link EVM chains contract addresses,
就一定要点击 "docs.chain.link - EVN Chains - Contract Addresses"
you can read more about the costs some of these different chains,
你可以在这里阅读到更多有关不同链上的价格信息
so you can figure out exactly how much to put in here.
这样你就能搞清楚到底该放进去多少资金了
And if you go to the full blockchain solidity course, Jas, we can scroll down to Lesson Nine,
如果你前往 "full-blockchain-solidity-course-js"，可以往下拉到 "Lesson 9"
there's a recommended link amounts or rinky saving tests
这里有一个针对 "Rinkeby Staging" 测试的 "LINK" 推荐数额
for chain link VRF. For now we're going to put two
对于 "Chainlink VRF" 我们建议填 "2"
for keepers, we're going to put eight,
对于 "Keepers" 我们建议填 "8"
but feel free to refer to here so you know how much to put in.
请自由参考这里的数值，这样你就能知道该填多少了
So let's go ahead and confirm, we're going to approve adding funds here,
让我们继续，点击 "Confirm"，然后就来到了 "Approve add funds" 界面
go ahead and confirm.
继续点击 "Confirm"
And we're now funding our subscription to
现在我们就为我们的订阅注入了资金
so we can pay that Oracle gas to get our random numbers.
这样我们就可以支付获取随机数所需的预言机 "gas" 了
Great. And once we're funded, we can close it, we'll do a little refresh.
好的，注资完成后，我们就可以关掉它了，再刷新一下
And we can see the balance is now to link
并且我们看到 "Balance" 现在是 "2 LINK" 了
when we don't have any consumers
不过我们还没有 "consumers"
perfect. So we've got our sub ID, we funded it.
完美，我们已经获取了我们的 "SubId"，并注入了资金
Now let's go ahead and deploy our contract.
现在让我们继续部署我们的合约
And we already know that we should be all good for deploying our contract,
不过我们知道，我们应该已经部署好我们的合约了
we go to our Dotty and V will need to add all of those same parameters from our previous projects,
前往我们的 ".env" 我们需要添加与上次项目中完全相同的参数
we'll need to shrink the RPC URL, we'll need our private key.
我们需要 "RINKEBY_RPC_URL"，以及我们的 "PRIVATE_KEY"
If we want to verify we'll need our ether scan API key.
如果我们想要验证的话，就还需要我们的 "ETHERSCAN_API_KEY"
And if we want to do gas output, we'll need our coin market cap API key.
以及，如果我们想要获取 "gas" 输出的话，那就还需要我们的 "COINMARKETCAP_API_KEY"
So let's make sure we have all that.
让我们来确认一下这里的所有内容
And we'll look at our deploy script. Once again, just real quick
查看一下我们的部署脚本，快速的看一下
look at our helper hardcat config just real quick,
再看一下我们的 "helper-hardhat-config.js"，同样是快速看一下
and it looks like we do indeed have everything in here.
看来我们这里确实已经具备所有的内容了
And we should just be able to deploy it in one command.
然后我们就应该用一行命令部署它了
So we should be able to do yarn, hard hat or just h h again,
我们应该运行 `yarn hardhat` 又或者是 `hh`
ploy, dash dash network Rinkeby.
`deploy --network rinkeby`
Let's go try this out.
来试一下吧
All right, it looks like we've compiled successfully, we've deployed it successfully. And we've even verified it,
很好，看起来已经编译成功并且部署成功，而且还验证完了
we can go and open it up on Rinku ether scan.
我们可以打开一下 "rinkeby.etherscan"
And we can see our code here has been verified. And it's looking beautiful.
可以看到我们的代码已经通过了验证，看起来非常漂亮
We can read from it, which is great. We can see all these commands here now that it's verified.
我们可以从中读取信息，好极了，还可以在这里看到所有的指令，并且都已经被验证了
And if we look at the Git raffle state, we should indeed see that it's open, right,
如果我们看一下这个 "getRaffleState"，应该能看到它是开放的，对吧？
and it's going to stay open until somebody ends the raffle and updates the amount of eath that the contract actually has.
并且它将一直保持开放，直到有人结束了抽奖并更新了合约实际拥有的以太币金额
Now that we've deployed a contract using that sub ID,
我们已经完成了使用 "SubId" 部署合约的任务
we need to register the contract with chain link V REF. And with chain link keepers.
现在我们需要为合约注册 "Chainlink VRF" 以及 "Chainlink keepers"
So we need to add this consumer does tell chinley VRF.
所以我们需要把它添加为 "consumer" 并告诉 "Chainlink VRF"
Hey, this is the contract that you're looking for now.
嘿，这就是你现在要找的合约了
So we're gonna go back to V REF dot chain dot link,
所以我们要回到 "vrf.chain.link"
and we're going to grab this contract address, and we're going to add it as a consumer,
我们要获取这个合约的地址，并将其添加为一个 "consumer"
your subscription is ready, you can now add consumers we're gonna add consumer.
你的订阅已经准备好了，现在可以添加 "consumer" 了，我们点击 "Add consumer"
And again, this website is just here to help facilitate us interacting with the contract.
再提醒一下，这个网站只是为了帮助我们更便捷地与合同进行交互而已
So we're going to approve that user, we'll go ahead and confirm and the transaction is going through.
这样我们就来到了用户批准环节，继续点击 "Confirm" 然后交易就正在进行了
While we wait for this to go through, we can go to keepers dot chain dot link,
当我们等待通过的时候，我们可以前往 "keepers.chain.link"
and do the same thing work with the user interface to register a new upkeep.
并在用户界面中使用同样的操作注册一个新的 "Upkeep"
So we'll go ahead and add our email Hardhead free code camp@gmail.com.
我们继续，添加我们的 Email: "hardhatfreecodecamp@gmail.com"
We'll call this raffle upkeep.
我们把它命名为 "Raffle Upkeep"
We'll paste our upkeep address in here
把我们的 "Upkeep address" 粘贴到这里
we have our admin address, and you can ignore this bit right here.
我们有一个 "Admin address"，你可以忽略这里的内容
For gas limit, this is going to be the gas limit of the PErforM upkeep function.
"Gas limit" 指的是 "performUpkeep" 函数的 gas 上限
If we did our gas estimator, we could just check to see how much that perform upkeep costs.
如果我们执行了 "gas estimator"，就能知道 "performUpkeep" 会消耗多少 gas
But for now, I'm just going to put 500,000 That's probably overkill, but that's fine.
但暂时我们先直接填上 `500000`，可能有点多了，不过没关系
Check data, we're going to keep blank because again, our checkup keep doesn't take anything.
"Check data" 这里我们会保持留白，因为我们的 "checkUpkeep" 没有接收任何参数
And then starting balance, we're going to put as eight.
而 "Starting balance" 我们就填入 `8`
And if you forget to put a starting balance here, you can always find it later.
如果你忘了填写这里的 "Starting balance"，可以之后随时填上
So let's go ahead and register,
那么让我们继续，点击 "Register"
we're gonna get a Metamask pop up, we're gonna go ahead and hit Confirm.
我们的 MetaMask 弹了出来，继续点击 "Confirm"
And we can go back to our VRF and see that it's indeed been added
然后我们可以回到 "VRF" 这里，并且能看到它确实已经被添加了
and awesome, we now have a consumer on our VRF.
好极了，现在我们的 "VRF" 上就有了一个 "consumer" 了
So now let's just wait for our keepers to go through
现在就让我们等一下 "Keepers" 的通过吧
upkeep registration requests submitted successfully
"Upkeep" 注册请求提交成功
on domain net, you might actually have to wait a little bit for your request to go through,
在主网上，你可能需要多等待一段时间请求才能通过
but I'll test that it should automatically go through.
但在测试网上它应该自动就通过了
Now if we go back to keepers dot chain dot link,
现在，如果我们回到 "keepers.chain.link"
we should now see we now if we scroll down to my upkeeps We have a raffle upkeep here
我们现在应该能看到，点开 "My upkeeps"，这里已经有了一个 "Raffle Upkeep" 了
and I have to because I accidentally use the same account that I tested on,
我有两个，因为我之前不小心用了相同的账号进行了测试
you can ignore the two you'll have one but this is the one that we just created.
你可以忽略这两个，有一个就行了，这一个才是我们刚刚创建的那个
And we can actually see what our balances and then what the minimum balance for this actually is.
我们可以看到我们的 "Balance" 以及 "Minimum Balance" 分别是多少
So it looks like eight Link was a little bit too low.
看起来 8 "LINK" 还有一点不够
So let's go back to Fosses dot chain dot link slash rinky.
所以让我们回到 "faucets.chain.link/rinkeby"
Now that we have some more link, we can come back to our raffle upkeep.
现在我们有了更多 "Link"，就可以回到我们的 "Raffle Upkeep"
And we go ahead and hit add funds.
我们继续，点击 "Add funds"
And we'll add just three. And we'll go ahead and confirm
我就添加 `3` 吧，继续点击 "Confirm"
we first need to give permission to spend.
首先我们需要得到花费许可
We approved our link transfer now let's actually transfer the link to the contract
我们批准了 "Link" 转移，现在让我们把 "Link" 实际转移到合约内
and alright funds added successfully. So now let's do a little refresh.
好的，资金添加成功，现在让我们刷新一下
Now we no longer see that message saying that it's underfunded and we have our balance
现在我们就不会看到资金不足的消息了，这是我们的余额
and we can see that it's more than the minimum balance.
并且我们可以看到，它是多于最小余额的
We have See the history that we just funded this twice.
我们可以在历史("History")中看到，刚刚我们注资了两次
Once this actually kicks off, we'll see activity type will be like perform upkeep or something
一旦这里被实际启动了，我们就能看到 "Activity type" 会变成 "performUpkeep" 之类的东西了
got our sub ID, we've deployed the contract, we've registered
with chain link V REF, we've registered it with chain link
keepers. Now all we need to do is run the staging tests. Now
running our staging test is essentially going to be the same
as us calling this enter script, right, because all we're doing
in our staging test is entering the lottery. And then we just
have a whole bunch of validators that we're running to make sure
that things are doing as we expect, since our contract is
actually verified, what we could do on Rigby ether scan is we can
actually go to this right contract section of the
contract. And we could even connect our wallets to it. And
once this turns from red to green, after a little refresh,
we'll now see that it's green, it's connected, we can even call
functions on this contract ourself, so we could enter the
raffle ourself, we would add, you know, however much eath to
enter the raffle, and that would kick off the keepers in the VRF,
as well. So we could call it via ether scan, we could obviously
call it via our staging tests here, we could call it via our
scripts, we could call it via the console, there's a ton of
ways to actually do this. But moment of truth here, we're
gonna run our staging tests, which is going to have us enter
the lottery, and set up a listener to make sure that
everything works correctly. And additionally, we'll see on our
raffle upkeep history, we'll see a transaction go through, and
then we'll see a transaction on our chain like VRF as well. Are
you ready? I sure am.
Let's do this. So we'll do h h, test, dash dash network, rink B.
And that should be all we need to do. In our state and tests,
we probably should have added some console dot logs in here to
tell us hey, to tell us what steps that we're on with each.
But we forgot to. So if you follow along with the repo
associated with this, we've added the console dot logs in
the test there. But all right, if we go to the ether scan for
this contract, we go back to the rink the ether scan for this, we
paste in that address, the first step that we're doing in this
test, of course, while we're setting up this listener, the
first transaction is going to be entering the raffle that's going
to kick everything off. Right. So if we refresh a little bit on
ether scan, we do indeed see we've entered the raffle. And
we've updated the balance of the raffle. Okay, awesome. So raffle
has been entered. Now then what happens? Well, if the raffle has
been entered, if we go to raffle dot soul, if it's open, if
enough time has passed, if there's players and it has a
balance, which we just checked does, this will get kicked off
by the keepers. So if we go to the keepers, and we do a little
refresh here, after a little bit, we do indeed see checkup
key passed and we see a perform upkeep having gone through
great, what does perform upkeep to well perform upkeep calls the
chainlink VRF. So now if we go over to chainlink, VRF, we do a
refresh here, go down to history, we do indeed see one of
the transactions has gone through we can see the
transaction hash, the link spent, etc. And now if we go
back to our tests, we do indeed see raffle unit tests for friend
fulfill random request winner pick event fired. And this means
that we just went through this entire process of having a
perfectly truly decentralized raffle work on an actual
Testament with our integration tests working correctly.
Absolutely massive, huge congratulations if you've made
it this far. And if you just walk through the integration
test with me now bounce over contract has now been reset to
zero because our wallet address just won the lottery right and
got the money back. Now you might be wondering, Hey, I see
the Create raffle function. And I see enter raffle but I don't
see didn't the chain link nodes just call perform upkeep and
fulfill random words, I'll come no matter how often I refresh, I
don't see those transactions here. Well, those are actually
going to be considered internal transactions fulfill random
words, it's actually called through the VRF coordinator and
the VRF coordinator contract then calls for full randomness.
So we can go to internal transactions. And one of these
transactions is going to be the transaction to the VRF
coordinator contract, which calls our contract. Same thing
with perform upkeep. Perform upkeep, the chain link nodes
actually call through the registry contract and then the
registry contract calls perform upkeep. That's what we see here.
And if we go through the internal transactions, we'll see
him there. Now let's look at this enter raffle as well. And
since we've learned about events and logs, we can actually go to
the logs section now. And we can see our log or event being
emitted here we can see the name raffle, enter, we can see the
topic zero which is going to identify this entire event. And
then we also see this number here which is what which is
index topic, one address player and then there's no data
associated with this right because we only have index
parameters which again show up as topics so this is absolutely
phenomenal.